A Guide to the Research Material for "Nancy Astor and Her Friends," 1920-1975
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Research Material for "Nancy Astor and Her Friends," 1920-1975
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7942-h
This collection consists of ca. 78 items.
Elizabeth Langhorne
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This material was given to the Library by Mrs. Elizabeth C. Lanhorne of Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 16, 1994.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of research materials, 1920-1966, and 1975, consists of ca. 78 items, pertaining to Elizabeth C. Lanhorne's book Nancy Astor and Her Friends. These preliminary research materials include original letters, newspaper clippings and other printed material, and handwritten research notes by the author. There is also an oversize item, an early autograph manuscript draft of the book, with heavy additions and revisions by the author.
Organization
The original folders which were marked with topics have been filed in permalife inserts with similar topic headings. These were early headings and do not exactly follow the book.
Contents List
- "Re death of Lord Philip Lothian"
  - Copy of letter from N[orman] H. D[avis] to Nancy Astor, December 13, 1940. (Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter from Nancy Astor to Eleanor Roosevelt, December 28, 1940. (Folder 1)
- "Re childhood and young adulthood of Nancy Witcher Langhorne (Lady Astor)" (Folder 1)
  - Letter from Simone Lahovany, lady in waiting to Marie, Queen of Roumania, to Mrs. [Charles Dana] Gibson, nee Irene Langhorne, October 20, 1926. (Folder 1)
  - Letter from "Aunt N--" [Nancy Astor] to Mrs. Harry F. [Elizabeth] Langhorne, May 23, 1956. (Folder 1)
  - Research notes and genealogy of the Langhorne family. (Folder 1)
- "Re House of Commons and Lady Astor" (Folder 1)
  - Pamphlet with speech "A Problem for Women" by the Viscountess Astor, February 24, 1920. (Folder 1)
  - Radio script concerning the "Romantic age of social reforms" about children be given the chance to flourish, 1931 (Folder 1)
  - Speech "Free by not Lawless" concerning "social progress since women got the vote"; and, printed material and research notes, 1937
- "Re Cliveden Set"
  - Letter from Lord Brand [Robert "Bob" H. Brand] to Mrs. Harry F. [Elizabeth] Langhorne, September 16, 1960. (Folder 1)
  - Copy of letter, Nancy [Astor] to "Buck" [William Henry Langhorne], October 12, n.y. (Folder 1)
- "Re a troubled peace"
  - Letter from Lady Nancy Astor to Edith (Forsythe) Langhorne, August 24, 1939. (Folder 1)
  - Article in Liberty entitled "George Bernard Shaw answers Frederick L. Collins about Lady Astor," March 11, 1939. (Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and research notes.
- "Re the last years of Lady Astor"
  - Letters from Douglas Langhorne to his mother, Mrs. William H. [Edith (Forsyth)] Langhorne, December 27, 1948; January 7, 1949. (Folder 2)
  - Printed material and newspaper clippings of obituaries and memorials to Lady Astor and re the Cliveden Set, and research notes, 1964-1965.
- "Re William Faulkner in South America"
  - Newspaper clippings and research notes, 1954-1961. (Folder 2)
  - Letters concerning Elizabeth Langhorne's planned visit to Bogota, Columbia, May-July 1975.
    Her visit was during the "Twentieth Seminar on the Acquisition of Latin American Library Materials" held on June 15-20, 1975.
  - Letter, Langhorne to Carlos Garcia Barron, Deputy Cultural Affairs Officer, Embassy of the United States of America, Lima Peru, May 6, 1975. (Folder 2)
  - Letter, Langhorne to Gabriel Garcia Marquez with bibliography of his work, May 24, 1975. (Folder 2)
  - Letter, Elizabeth C. Evans, Caracas, Venezuela, to Langhorne, July 1975 (Folder 2)
  - Letter, Dr. Vytautas A. Dambrava, Cultural Affairs, Embassy of the United States of America, Caracas, Venezuela, to Langhorne, July 2 [sent September 9], 1975. (Folder 2)
- "Re Langhorne family"
  - Pamphlet entitled "Chiswell Dabney Langhorne 1843-1918" (Folder 2)
  - Typescript "Buck Langhorne and Sam Goodloe" by Holman Willis, Roanoke, Virginia"
- 8" x 10" watercolor of mountain scenery through trees, signed "F. S. Coles '79." (Folder 3)
- Early autograph manuscript draft of Nancy Astor and Her Friends,n.d. (Oversize M-19)
  Includes additions and revisions by the author.